whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases so I'm so glad you're
both joining me here for this and I have
a sense of how to proceed here and the
first thing I ask we do is that we take
30 seconds of silence together and after
that silence I'm going to open a space
as it were I have a sense perhaps of
what a link one of many between us is
and I would presence that and not put
that link or that frame before being
here now together more as a departure
point and we'll see where we land and
then we are then we are off so if that
sounds good then perhaps we can take 30
seconds of silence here I'm going to
shut my eyes please feel free to do
whatever is most natural yeah I will do
the same okay
oh so it is a real pleasure in an
uncertain time to be here with you both
over the last four to five months I've
had the privilege of speaking with both
of you separately on a few Kate on a few
occasions each now and both of those
conversations have been deeply
meaningful to me and meaningful to many
I know who have listened and perhaps
even transformative for me and my sense
is the wisdom inherent in the embodiment
I have been present to in each of you as
well as in the theory that each of you
have been developing on and Express is
one that is in an important sense deeply
resonant and well worth present sing
together although of course I don't just
mean the theory so my hope is that in
this conversation we come all of get to
know each other and generate insight
informative of you understanding that is
beneficial and helpful really up and
down the stack for for for ourselves
each other others and not in any way
disconnected from from mind and heart
and soul and what have you and the sense
I have of and here I'll present
something that is as well core to the
core insight that is moving me and
driving me to express and realize things
in the world in conformity with or being
informed by is the following and perhaps
we can take that as a departure point
and that is this dynamic of the
relationship between authentic
expression and how it is met in
relationship in its context and here I'm
going to use words that I know are
resonant with each of you in perhaps
slightly different ways but to that and
hopefully bring our vocabulary and sense
together the expression of authenticity
when it is met in an environment of care
and perhaps a few other things although
I don't want to belabor us with too many
words when authentic expression is met
with care we have here a core dynamic of
the of the dynamic of growth and when
authentic expression is truncated
perhaps traumatized we have here the the
opposite we have here the retraction of
the opportunity for growth in the
extreme and there's links here with this
with notions of voluntary confrontation
you know of a fear of uncertainty and we
have here also notions of the value of
stepping into vulnerability we also
presencing the importance of
relationship and this dynamic between
individual and context and self and
other so i from here as a framing I see
this as being something important to all
of us and deeply informative of the of
the ideas and ultimately embodied way we
might
realize in our lives and together and
I'm interested in how that lands for
both of you so that's that's all I have
to say powerful framing I guess I would
say I'd want to pull out two of the
central things that were sort of anchor
points on what you said this idea of
authentic dialogue authentic discourse
and part of what I would like to explore
is the possibility of opening both of
those back up putting them into question
and you know in a high to garyun sense
what do we mean by authenticity I think
it's I mean Heidegger is perhaps the
person who made that you know a way of
speaking
and but I imagine it has drifted quite
away from what it could be for us I'd
like to what I'm saying is I want to
open these both up in a reciprocal
questioning what do we mean what are we
trying to get at when we're trying to
get out of often disappear to dialogue
or what I'd like to call deal logos and
how do those two opening up how do they
relate to each other because I think
you're right there's a there's people
are at least the people I'm coming into
communication with people are hungry for
a kind of connectedness that
simultaneously grounds them and affords
them also growth and transformation they
have a there's a hunger for this but
they feel that a lot of the ways the
terms and the concepts they bring to
bear to try and express it are not
translating into transformative practice
and so there seems to me to be a gap
between the conceptual framework we're
using to try and express this and the
ability to achieve the goals that we're
pursuing in the expression so that's
kind of what I'm interested in in this
framing
I guess what comes up for me right away
around that is this the paradoxes of of
where actually is the self so I'm
assuming that there's if we're gonna be
starting with this notion of
authenticity that we would be tapping
into something that was something
sincerely within me that I could share
with you and the paradox there is that
that I know of course I would offer you
everything I would gladly unzip myself
and be there but I have this this kind
of interesting tension of recognizing
that if I did what you would see is all
the ways in which the context that I
have lived with in the experiences that
I have had the the you know the traumas
from school and being wrong and the the
way in which you know maybe right now
our speech patterns are getting judged
that those would be indications and they
would be they would be an illustration
of all the ways in which that thing that
I would wish to unzip and show you that
would be truly mine is actually of the
context that I have been in and I
honestly have no idea how to tell the
difference I would like to be able to
say and Here I am in my most authentic
self
but what the heck is that and how could
I possibly extract that or find this
this nugget or essence even because I
think there is a kind of yearning to get
at that essence that is somehow
untouched by my culture my experience my
my my life my ancestors life my you know
my children's lives my and I think
especially right now in this moment
where there's so much melting in the
structures around us that this is a
question that bears a lot of
consideration around if I am shaped and
formed and forged in the the various
structures that I have lived within Who
am I when those structures are gone I
think that's really important how what I
understanding is saying and of course
please interject if I miss frame you but
there is I think you're doing part of
what I wanted to do which is the
automaticity by which authenticity is
understood in terms of a reconnection
with one's inner true self is very is
very much the thing I want to bring into
question and that assumed idea that we
have this stables for the Cartesian
subjectivity within us that that is the
ultimate normative guide for our entire
life is precisely the thing
not paradoxically ironically which was
Heidegger introduced the term
authenticity to try and call all that
into question and now it has somehow
circled around it is somehow circled
around there authenticity is if that
shows you how pervasive almost parasitic
that that that formulation of thinking
we want to call it the question is how
it can take something that was so
carefully crafted to call it into
question and absorb it back into itself
and say no no this is what it means and
this is what we've always been talking
about
III find that for something that we
should also just step back and pause on
right away and say notice how this how
the very thing was supposed to challenge
all of this got reabsorbed into the very
machinery it was trying to challenge I
think that's that should give us some
pause for how carefully we need to work
together on this right now because
there's a lot happening in our cultural
cognitive grammar in our background
that's gonna keep driving us back
towards that the very thing it's gonna
drive us towards a closure the very
thing we're trying to bring into
question but I hope I understood you
Nora because that's what that's the
connection I'm getting from what you
said that's that's exactly where I want
to go and I mean even language and
certainly communication patterns become
a kind of reflection of repetition of
extension of these various contextual
threads that say this is who I am this
is and when I want to say yeah but this
is the real me where's the real me and I
think that that there have been moments
and I think those moments of confusion
might be something really to look into
and that those moments where I prior to
the past couple of weeks my most
frequent experience of moments of
confusion that maybe had something of
that
what do I even want to call it is it's
something raw okay I'll just say it's
something wrong so it is when I live in
in Sweden and I live in I do a lot of a
lot of my life in multiple cultures so I
mean Rana which is inherently
multicultural place very multicultural
place please go ahead yeah so one of the
things that can happen is that you I
have found that I could think that I
have expressed something and and then
realised that that is not what was
received and get very kind of
disoriented in the reception in the way
the reception is reflected back to me
and and there's a something that happens
there that is is like a crack in the
matrix of my various contextual
formations and language and and those
cracks those cracks might be the closest
I know to to getting at this thing and
and and right now I think there's an
awful lot of cracks of looking around
and thinking you know really who who are
we what what do I say what what can we
possibly say in this moment being is
authentic and the second I try to make
it authentic it becomes in effect ik for
sure yeah I just I understand that was a
good point you made about how you know
that pattern that I was pointing to sort
of historically with Heidegger is also
something we find prevalent in our own
attempts I was what called to mind was a
Leonard Cohen song and he talks about
you know the crack that lets you know
that lets the light right yeah and so
this leads me to
this leads me to well somebody who
practiced introducing those cracks as a
way of trying to provoke wonder and I'd
like to at some point talk about the
difference between wonder which calls
this self and the world into question
and curiosity which tries to feed and
plug up the gaps in the self and and the
worldview and so but I'm so and and had
a lot to say about a dialogical notion
of the self and I'm thinking here of the
figure of Socrates that I'm and somebody
I'm working to try and understand very
deeply precisely because he had a form
of communicative practice that centered
upon introducing those cracks getting
people to a place of aporia where it was
possible it was not inevitable not
inevitable but it was possible for them
to come to a state of wonder that
opening where they could call the the
the self and the world into question and
then they and that could induce them to
see the self as something that is
aspired to as opposed to something that
has already possessed and so I'm very
interested in all of that and the
question and the work I've been doing
with Peter Lindbergh and guys tense talk
and Chris master Pietro is is it
possible for us I'm changing the
question slightly nor don't I hope
you'll be patient with me is it possible
for us to learn from that such that we
could be better able to pursue what
we're trying to pursue right now which
is getting some sense of how to move
towards deeper communication deeper
community in a way that people are
craving so that's for me how I'm trying
to think about this right now I'm trying
to think about it in terms of people
have managed in past to give us examples
and to be exemplars of how to do the
thing we're doing and what
it mean for us to learn from them well
first of all can we learn from them and
then what does it mean for us to learn
from them and how do we bring that about
[Applause]
Tim are you there still yeah we'll have
to see how we do this is a bit of an
unlikely occurrence the internet hasn't
had any problems since I've moved into
this apartment I'm going to open the
door to the bedroom so we're getting our
own aporia here a lot of the cracks are
shining coming right now for us so
technology is the God that limps opening
the door to let the internet in this is
that's next level my friend Internet in
you know yeah yeah yeah the sacrifice is
my girlfriend's extra a couple hours of
sleeping here so there has been a cost
to this door opening does it actually
work to open the door to let the
internet look I mean I don't understand
how signals work but there seems to be a
physical world where there are some
interactions and that's the level of
madness by which I'm approaching this
environment but as far as I'm concerned
it may be possible at least you know I
care it's my favorite thing all day yeah
it's how I sew for my problems actually
but please get serious here and let's
get to work mmm all right so I was I was
proposing a model that we could consider
for somebody who regularly like I said
he he crafted the virtue of inducing the
cracks in people the aporia which let
the light shine through of a new
possibility of self and also a new
possibility of world
you know that's that's wonder as just
and I follow fuller and other people and
seeing wonder is very different from
mere mere curiosity and that ability to
induce wonder and to put the bring
people to a place it wasn't inevitable
but it was possible where they could
aspire to a different self and a
different world is is I think a valuable
example for us to consider precisely
because the the Socratic model of
authenticity is an aspirational model
their true self is not something you
possess and it's not something you
possess in distinction from others or
your world it's something that you
aspire to continually and never in any
kind of completion to an ongoing process
of mutual transformation and although
I'm not claiming we can get back that
would be an Akron Akande and therefore
fallacious to Socrates or the Socratic
world although there are some very
important similarities Socrates was
carrying out his practice while Athens
is literally under siege the whole city
is quarantined and there had been a
plague so his context is not that
different from ours in some important
ways I'm recommending that we that we
take a look at Socratic dialogue as a
way of perhaps speeding up the process
by which we can learn about how to
recover a relational sentence of self
and an operational sense of authenticity
perhaps that are urgently needed right
now and then that's on and I propose
that to Nora and then she added
something to say about it um yeah I
really love that you're taking it to
this place John because this is kind of
where I'm working with all my hours and
moments and days and heart and soul
right now and I have been generating
these
okay let's call them dialogues but
there's they're sort of I called them
warm data labs okay so the idea is that
there's an exploration of a complex
question with a number of people and
that exploration includes them starting
in small groups around various contexts
and then they move when they want to but
if I don't ring a bell and make a move
they go where they want when they want
and things get mixed up this is you know
back in the days when people could be in
the same room together so what I started
to witness happening with that was
really interesting because as people to
explore to question whether that
question is something like you know what
is health or what is identity or what is
authenticity could even be one look that
that becomes something that is very
swiftly revealed in the stories and the
inputs between the people as being
something that exists between the
contexts and between the people so it
started a liminal revealer and an
interdependency revealer and and and so
I guess where I'm going with that is
that the the more of those processes
that I have done and I've been doing
hundreds of them around the world the
more I I'm seeing how important it is
that that process of opening those
cracks of coming into that that wonder
is actually it's not to be done alone no
we actually need each other to provide
multiple description and by that I don't
just mean lots of perspectives I
so mean lots of textures of ways of
talking so it's not just my professional
knowledge or or just my personal stories
right you have to have both of those and
questions and jokes and things that come
up between people that are unexpected
and that in a strange way in the the
most intimate kind of shiftings happen
in this possibility of having multiple
patterning 'he's kind of overlay like a
more a phenomenon mm-hmm so that in that
more a phenomenon there becomes I guess
one of the signatures of them soiree is
that you have one pattern and then you
have another pattern and when you cross
them you have a third pattern and a
third pattern can actually tell you
something about either of the other
patterns but it isn't right and so what
I'm getting at is that a kind of insight
can come out of that overlay and and so
this is where where those insights are
not actually accessible very often in
life and in this moment I'm with you
there's an urgency so this process that
I've been playing with is actually kind
of an accelerated an accelerated inter
dependency insight maker that's great
that's amazing that's really cool it's
really cool yeah I'm very excited about
this so if we could unpack this just a
little the practice I don't know how
much you know of my work that I've been
engaging in a lot of participant
observation and a lot of these emerging
I call them cyclic technologies or these
practices of trying to afford insight
and flow within you know within dialog
within you know distributed cognition
and so it's really
you know and also people trying to put
things together
it's what I'm saying is there's this
interesting conversion so for example
I've been participating in circling and
then they're they're trying to get
circling to integrate with you know
bringing in important topical questions
so how do we go from just circling where
we're maintaining the circle to making
it topical in a fashion and and then
what are the bridging processes you do
because if you just sort of slam people
from circling to a topic they can get
sort of they can the coherence can break
and so I'm it's really interesting about
how a lot of things seem to be coming
you know towards each other so I can I
ask you some more
I don't know this isn't the right
adjective so but be forgiving on it can
I ask you some more technical questions
more specific questions about so sorry
this is what I'm just gonna be a little
bit of a cognitive scientist here for a
moment because I'm really really
intriguing this one thing and and and
and this is something that pattern I've
I'm not trying to take anything away for
you I've thought about doing that
because that's very similar about you
know this sort of small world network
formation you get within a brain to
provoke insight within and I was
wondering if we could get that sort of
fluid small world network restructuring
between people that would also bring
about an insight and it seems like
you've actually already cottoned onto
this and made it work so that is that is
really fascinating and then I'm what I'm
really interested in well there's
multiple things use what you said is
just writing me up right now I'm
interested in what's the relationship
between you know the group insight if
you Lana and the individual insights how
are they resonating with each other how
is that working and then the thing you
talked about with the patterns that
Chris and I talked about that in the
article the chapter we've written about
this sort of third factor that emerges I
see it encircling all the time in which
you get you get so you'll get people
will get into this like two people than
these people and then that gets layered
and you get that emergent this what we
call the third factor I can give it sort
of an extensive reference without a very
just cleared a notation and I'm real and
what's interesting is people's eye
I want to ask you if this is also the
huh like do people sense that like do
they get a sense of something telling
them or calling them to move from one
one of the groups to another and do they
get a sense of you know that something
is taking shape like a light that has a
sort of a systemic life of its own above
and beyond not only the individuals but
the subgroups because I'm definitely
finding that you know reported
continuously when I'm doing the
participant observation of these other
kinds of practices is that is that also
going on in the one day - laughs
absolutely and and one of the things
that happens is that it it I mean I I
did a lot of systems teaching and
complexity teaching and it was frankly
irritating because you know people would
come and we'd have these great workshops
and people who understood it before felt
very clever and the people who didn't
understand it maybe had a little sense
of it for a little while but then it
would kind of fade away it would either
away from them and here's what I'm
finding is that they're the the
structure of the process has to do with
creating the opportunities for about so
the people can have a conversation about
the question of what is health through
the context of economy and then they can
move over to family and and in those
little circles they tell all sorts of
stories and all kinds of stuff you
there's absolutely no conscious purpose
control over what gets talked about
there's no documentation very important
no documentation what do you mean
specifically by that it's not recorded
or people aren't allowed to cite staff
or what does that mean I usually don't
do either okay okay there's no post-its
there's no paper tablecloths there's
nobody writing anything down because
those contextual interactions the story
that you tell me about your grandmother
whose recipe reminds me of something and
that is a link like compo
finding links finding relational process
right and so that that is and then I go
to another context and someone says
something and it connects then to your
grandmother's story and the memory that
that brought me to and so that this
understanding of if you want to call it
systemic soar complexity or inter
dependency whatever you want to call
that it turns out to be very intimate so
is the idea that there there there
exemplifying it now right there
instantiated there participating in it
they're not just sort of talking about
it
yeah well what's happening is there's an
about and there's a within ah right
right
so the the conditions of the lab are
structured to offer the space for people
to talk about right but in the negative
space of it there's the liminal of
what's actually connecting in the within
so you never have a warm data lab on
relationships or communication because
that would be ridiculous those are all
things that are forming in the within
yeah right so so that's been really
interesting and then after the lab
there's this moment that I would call
the mutual learning moment so then
there's a sort of a moment when we have
the room in plenary and say so you know
what did you notice what have you
observed and that's when you get that
group lift but most don't actually have
words for what they've experienced
because it's been such a combination of
intellectual and physical and emotional
and memory and all these things have
been kind of mushing and reconnecting
and they're in a territory they've never
actually had to make words for before
hmm but a couple of people in the room
will find the words and when they start
to find the words the other people also
find words
and the words are usually something
along the lines of I started to notice
that I you know there was repeated
things in multiple contexts that there
was overlap that when I left one context
the conversation that I had there didn't
go out of my body I took it with me it
was ease into the next conversation and
so you get this lift that happens in
that moment where the whole room
realizes that they've had very different
experiences but they've had a they've
had a mutual learning at the same time
so this idea that mutual learning
doesn't mean we're learning the same
thing look it means we're learning
together and that that is as unique for
you or me or you know anybody of any age
and and really I've been working with
this in very vulnerable communities and
also in Parliament's so in inner-city
Pittsburgh with groups of Islamic women
in Asia in really broken towns in the UK
and then with the Finnish politicians or
with very so it's really it kind of
anyone can do it kids can do it for sure
yeah it's pretty interesting so have you
has this been written down anywhere or
have you liked because I'd like to learn
more about it and we have limited time
here maybe you and I could I mean how
does one learn to practice it because
come on take our now so it's it's a it's
there's a lot of theory there and so to
bring this kind of back to where we are
with this conversation I think probably
one of the most important pieces is the
piece around
abductive process and
and that that is the piece where it
starts to become clear in this question
of of authenticity that there is a kind
of cross contextual description that we
live within everyone lives within it in
fact I would say probably every living
thing lives within a cross contextual
description so if you look at an
earthworm that earthworm is a
description in a way of the soil it's
also a description of the tree or of the
bird or of the grandpa and grandson that
are going to go fishing or right so that
earthworm is is just like you and I are
a description of our education system
we're a description of our culture we're
and in these different contexts are
difficult to grab hold of and fix
in isolation are in reductionism because
they're actually not where they you grab
them and they're not there you want to
fix the education system but it's
actually it's actually creative in the
abductive process of our economy and
culture and intergenerational
expectations and identity and you know
all these things that then you know the
education system is a consequence right
right because I see here John if I can
just to know we are track do it no no no
no no no no no not at all
just to draw some things together and
make sure that I'm up and with this and
also perhaps is to add a little bit so
if I can synthesize sort of some of the
themes we've we've touched on so far and
importantly authenticity is not the the
expression or the capturing of something
that is the inherent and importantly
fixed to you but something that is
realized in a some form of cooperative
but ultimately interdependent dynamic on
an ongoing basis with each other so we
are we are present seeing from a
phenomenological perspective that we are
talking more than that a question might
be what is it to show up to
transformation to learning to the
drawing forth and and remembering of
engaging in a remembering of what it is
to be with each other and also an
aspiration of our becoming and deepening
together too so what we can perhaps add
in although not to jump the gun is what
are some of these modes of orientation
and this is something I've thought a lot
about what are ways we show up actually
to these moments of when the moment is
upon us
John you like to use this term Kairos
that there is a significant imminence to
the now where we
maybe particularly challenged or call up
called upon to presents ourselves in an
appropriate or right relationship with
each other given the given a kind of
particular energetic context thrust upon
us and it seems to me we if we really
were to not be reductive but but attempt
to synthesize some core modes we might
take in response to this we can we can
allow ourselves to be moved by this
process in a way that's appropriate and
we can allow ourselves as well to more
confront and move this process too so
there's a sort of a push and pull
dynamic that can be done effectively or
less effectively and a lot of that I
think has to do with how well we are
able to sense what is the appropriate
ripening vulnerability to step into with
a certain kind of care and courage
rather than to rather than to either
bury our heads when faced with a moment
or in fact to attempt to close that
opening before in fact we were able to
find and be with each other in order to
then come to some kind of harmony or
movement together so and I think this
can help ground us as well back in what
some of the experiences are we're having
in our lives at the moments because fear
of course is very much heightened and
care and courage are very much called
for in this time and it is my hope in a
deeper sense that the kind of theory we
might be discussing in this conversation
is in actual fact a crucial piece at
more than a crucial piece that all of
this together is very much involved in
the movement towards the realization of
we because that is also what we are
discussing here how can we create these
mutual learning environments where we
can give and receive to our fullest as
best we can informative and enabling of
transformation both individually and
collectively in touch with ecology so
grounding this back in our moment today
I think is important because the
emotionality people
experiencing and attention they're
experiencing in their lives
I think we're ultimately are making
calls here that there are a call for
stepping into that moment holding
oneself in such a way that enna enables
us to transform that toward a wholeness
not a final one Whitehead has this
expression the many become one and are
increased by one which is a process
framing of some of what we are
discussing here so to add some of these
pieces in am I sort of on track with
some of the core features of our
discussion I think so I I mean there's
two things I guess I'd want to say first
to respond to you and then to thread
back to to Norah I think what we're
talking about here in the thing and I
mean there is like yeah I see this as a
feature of many of these emerging
practices there's this oscillation
between theory and theory aware I mean
using theory in the old sense of the
word you know the contemplative
immersive involvement that you know
gives you insight and then there's
reflective theory that that movement is
and trying to figure out what some of
those patterns are not just for theories
sake because I think what what Nora is
doing and you know what guys doing the
circling I like what Nora's doing though
because it's got this topical element to
it that I think is really important in
central and it's got this ability it's
got its got a grammar built in of of you
know explicit restructuring and the way
people move around and I think these are
important things to take note of and
that's why I was taking note of them but
towards your question Tim is that these
practices give people a deep taste what
I call a participatory and perspective
of knowing of the power and the
potential of you know of our I don't
like this term and but it's you know of
our sense making and our meaning making
capacities if people know the thing
people will take significant hits to
their standard of living
if they get a sense a you know a felt
sense of a course of mattering a course
of the enhanced connectedness that's why
people have children I mean it having a
child is completely irrational from a
subjective point of view because your
health goes down your finances go down
you're tired all the time your most
significant relationship is it's put
into Christ like every all of your
subjective well-being just crashes when
you have a child you ask people why they
do it they do it because they want it
they feel connected and involved with
and involved with not just theorizing
about they feel participatory in the
creation of something that transcends
them in an important way so giving
people if you can give these practices
have a value I would argue in helping
people remember in you know in their in
the sense of sati right mindfulness
deeply remember you know and I want to
use this taste metaphor like in the
Bible you know taste the Lord and see
that he is good right they can they can
remember what this is like what it's
like to be immersed in this to flow with
this and I think that gives people a
kind of faith encourage that is deeply
realizable and relevant right here right
now that's so yes on being the nerdish
scientist and I'm really excited and
interested about what Noor is talking
about you know as a scientist but I
think I can make I think I just made it
there's a case for this the existential
import of what we're discussing I think
is also apparent and should be should be
noted
that's not how I would response year
that sort of reframing I think they here
I think we're there is we have we can
have a kind of stereoscopic vision where
the the theoretical concern and the
existential concern are both actually
being infused into a kind of depth in
which that is a value to us right here
right now hmm well that seems to be
called for in this time and I wonder if
the framing of the concepts of the
interior and the exterior is part of
what is may be helpful to presence here
as well so core to how I've been one way
I've been attempting to communicate the
project I've been on with this for some
years is to and I'm not like I'm not
happy with this framing necessarily
there's other things I would prefer to
say but what I have been saying
explicitly in places is the process of
making sense of what to care about and
of course it's more like caring about
making sense of what to care about but
there's because there's this there's a
sense in which these things are so
interdependent yet there is an
orientation towards I think ultimately
grounded in something like of love and
for love that's I think better made
better related to in a language of
perhaps care or towards that
metaphorical way rather than sense but
we are here in this moment together
where so much is shifting and it's how
can we draw in what is most relevant and
also be anchored in what is what is most
worth caring about
and so it's bringing these two together
in the process absolutely that seems to
be so fundamental well I mean that's
Socrates taught erotica
Socrates knew how to care and that's a
central idea in Heidegger like the the
the the the you know the wisdom of
caring well and you know that's where I
think and I want to turn it back to Nora
now that's what I think the work I do on
relevance realization seems to line up I
think I have a sense I'm not clear yet
but it seems at least it's convergent
with what she stopped talking about when
she's talking about
sort of
this abductive process that's at work
because that comes up a lot in in in in
my work too and so I want to turn it
back to normal and I want to hear more
about this abductive process mmm yeah
the abductive process is really
interesting because I'm pretty sure that
that's where the change actually is and
it's something that is is largely
missing from most of the diagrams of and
explanations of systems change there's
it's actually in the abductive process
that you're going to get the real shift
and and that's really I would say in in
my sort of verbage around this that's a
very trends contextual yeah it's
happening across them through multiple
content and it requires that and we do
it all the time anyway mmm it's just a
matter of allowing for a different
abductive process so if if I'm in an
abductive process where my identity is
formed through and across the various
institutions of our world my education
my job my family my wealth my economy my
health my sexuality my gender my right
all of these things and and and all of
them are describing each other that's
that's the piece that when it when you
get it it's like oh that there it is but
it's a little tricky to do in a you know
40-minute podcast but the thing is is
that in there there is another kind of
integrity so when when I'm seeing
abductive shift in groups with groups of
people
I don't guide it know I just make a
space for it and this is actually
critical
I don't ever ever make any inclination
of what I think people should learn or
could come out the other end of this
thinking because I feel like that is
absolutely not my territory I can make a
space for those connections to happen
but they should be alive they should be
as complex and as unique as every person
in that room with infinite possibilities
of connecting their ideas and stories
and inputs so it's it's very alive and
that living thing is totally
unpredictable at the same time it's
pretty predictable every time I've done
it there's been a shift um and so I just
don't know what the details of that
shift are I don't get to voice or shape
or define or in any way describe that
shift I can only make a space for it so
what people are able to do when they
start to move across those contexts as
they can see the way in which they are
interdependent and that perception
without any effort has the second-order
response of a kind of integrity it has
to do with recognizing not integrity
around what's right or wrong but
integrity to show up and respond in ways
that are inclusive of that
interdependence II as opposed to just
looking at one one sort of solution in
one context at a time or or one one
trauma in one context at a time you know
so often trauma gets put into really
reductionist terms and so there's a kind
of a therapeutic and a healing quality
to this that is that think what we're
talking about when we say people are
longing this connection that in in that
longing what happens is that when you
start to see that this thing that is a
trauma that you might be carrying is not
actually it's not actually located in
any particular context it's moving
between all of them and other people are
sharing other traumas that are woven
between all these different contexts and
suddenly that trauma isn't as internal
it becomes something that is a
perceivably contextual and trans
contextual which is an enormous relief
and when I say it's warm data it's it's
like literally warm you can literally
feel the warmth of that so it's it's
interesting to see that and especially
in this moment which i think is a moment
of a need for a completely it's a need
to integrate in another way yeah so how
do we begin to create the conditions for
people to integrate together into a way
of seeing and and responding to this
time I think that's an excellent
question
and I'm particularly interested in one
aspect of that question that I alluded
to or I mentioned earlier which is I'm
interested in what are the conditions
that afford insight for people and how
those interact with what are those what
are the conditions that afford insight
between people and how and then there's
kind of a third thing what is the what
is sort of the optimal relationship
between the the the individual insight
and the collective insight and that's
something I'm trying to get a deeper
understanding of III think that the fact
that people are enacting and literally
moving
and they're embodying the
interdependence I think that is probably
playing a very significant role in in
the practice because you know you're
triggering the cerebellum you're getting
people to literally reorient their
visual processing what they're
foregrounding and back rounding is
literally shifting we know that those
kind of processes trigger individual
insight and then if they're and if that
if that's an insight that also you know
gets them to realize the interdependence
then I can see how the groups would also
restructure collectively so that various
things are again being facilitated it's
interesting about this maybe I can form
a question around that bridge that I've
just made because when you look within
individual cognition inducing
criticality you have to introduce some
significant amount of disruption like if
if you hear somebody's trying to solve
an insight problem on a computer screen
you put some static or some noise and it
put its a bit of entropy in it or you
allow or or you moderately distract them
not to distracted so they leave the
problem but enough that they'll sort of
you know they get you break up the
stability and that criticality actually
affords the restructuring like the way a
sand pile will self organize and then it
avalanches and that affords a new
structure so I'm wondering if if if you
if you see that playing a role within
the one data that there's there's you
know there's there's there's there's is
there a presence of disruptive
strategies sort of being played with you
know in contrast but interdependently
with constructive strategies you're
seeing that the criticality in the
construction are sort of mutually
interpenetrating is that happening
absolutely because when people go into
so if you get up from one context and
you walk over to another one
what is induction yeah yeah right you
you have to actually you know come into
that so there's a lot of what's
happening who's here there's a whole
process of paying attention in ways that
are all sorts of nonverbal attention and
then
in engaging in that conversation and
bringing with you this conversation that
just came on board and maybe the one
before that because it's usually the
third context that you start to get the
the pop yeah that makes sense to me and
it's it's also being in a room where
there are all those contexts so you have
you're in a room where there is this
meta right and that background to some
degree right that's right yeah and so
that you don't get to forget that you're
in this meta which is really interesting
it it actually it really decreases the
possibility for polarization which is
really really interesting especially in
you know in these times where there's
been so much polarization that you know
usually we go traveling down a rabbit
hole because we feel like there's some
context someone's not seeing and but if
it's in the room and it's just over
there you can just go over there it's
not people are less prone to positioning
yeah so there's that and that is I guess
you could call that a disruptor but it's
a gentle one yeah I think it's also you
know you don't wanna you don't want to
break the system right now you've got to
perturb it because if you don't perturb
it enough you know it'll get into a
local minima it'll stabilize prematurely
and then people can often not you know
explore this space of possibilities as
deeply as as is probably needed and the
other thing is that I think that you
talked about topics yeah and one of the
things that is really important is to
not have topics where people have
scripts so that's an interesting
question how do you do that because you
know a lot of the a lot of the things
you brought up as examples struck me as
one which people often have you know
pretty firm opinions that have a lot of
cultural
Baga to touch them like health for
example like you know people have lots
of opinions about health of course now
even more so and there's all this
cultural valuation of health han says
you know that health has become our God
in some ways it's every it's the thing
that justifies everything else we do so
what does that mean that that's very
provocative what you just said how would
you bring up like that let's do that one
because it's actually relevant to how
would you bring up health and keep it
off script how does that work well you
might bring up family hmm okay if I was
working with a bunch of doctors
um I might bring use family health be
one of the contexts I see I see so that
you get this right you get it off-center
so that you can actually reorient and
read that the abductive processes move
in other ways
oh that's very good that's very good
yeah because these centering strategies
also are things found with an individual
cognition and insight so it's
interesting of that murren that's really
cool
I had one recently and and this I think
Tim this really is important with your
question around authenticity because
this is this is kind of critical is how
to get off of these scripts and the
scripts have meaning and have have I
haven't have a set of signaling and
receiving possibilities within
relationships if you if you are in a set
of different relationships those
signaling zs-- don't go anywhere
you can still signal they just kind of
dud so it's it's something to get off
context too if you have a bunch of you
know doctors talking about media for
example and family and suddenly that
there's all kinds of health stuff that
is implicit in there
and it connects in but it isn't what
they're saying so it's this thing of not
going for the direct corrective which is
going to generate all sorts of
reductionist scripted maybe I don't know
how that connects to authenticity but I
know that when people don't know what
they're gonna say and they haven't said
that thing before and they were
considering the the thing that was going
to come from the person that just said a
thing that that they they enter into a
discourse in another way they enter into
a mutual learning in a way that
surprises even them but I think that's
excellent connection to authenticity
Nora I mean there's a deep connection
between getting off script and what
we're trying to do here I mean right it
is in this special identity is we're
trying to get I mean there's kind of a
meta level we're trying to get off
script about authenticity and it's now
it's now that well part of what this
attempt to reformulate authenticity is
is centering on is the very capacity and
ability to get off script but do it like
you said you have to do it in this if
you do it you know you have to do it in
a certain way you have to pick you have
to get it like if it's health and you go
off center because you actually talk
about family you wouldn't talk about
like elephants for example right you
it's about it's you've got it like so
there's finesse in the sense that
there's finesse in this if you know I'm
a Tai Chi player and there's this sense
about you know a can you can you pick up
on the grain of things and follow the
grain and and get a sense of how you
know well you know you're sparring with
somebody as you said you know you don't
just hit them because they'll just flock
but can you get them off center and then
there's possibilities that open up and
so I think I think I like what you just
said I like this idea about a connection
between a rican sexual ization perhaps
of authenticity by connecting it to
getting people off script in you know in
a way that shows finesse and affords
inside it I think that's a very I think
that
very powerfully connected to what we're
talking about with authenticity yeah
that all of this rings very true and
there's some things I can presence here
that I think are vital and I supposed to
go metal on it the turn is for me to
speak personally the reason for that is
when we drop into the personal and move
towards where we are vulnerable this has
an effect on
setting the context within which other
participants may or may not be willing
to go and so here why John you you
reference finesse because of course
there are the three of us here but there
are also more than the three of us here
at least potentially and this is very
significant and this is an obstacle not
an obstacle without it's an opportunity
but an obstacle we all here face this
notion of off-script is something that
has had much resonance with me for a
long time I in fact set up an event last
year
I hired out a theater and the event was
called off script and I attempted to
have people come along to that event but
I cancelled it because I could not get
anyone to come so the question is how
then do you invite a setting where
can't go off-script because the price is
high the price of admission is much
higher than a ticket because really if
we were to open up again to the
significance we are here a part of this
moment we are in in the world the
vulnerability there the confrontation
with death and perhaps worse that is
there the various ways in which we may
or may not have been seen with each
other in this on this ride towards that
which we perceive as perhaps ending and
in suffering I think all magnifies each
other and so
yes things are about going off-script
and they always have been and whether or
not we were aware of it part of us
always was we just lost awareness of it
even as we ran out certain programs and
mistook perhaps programs before the
totality but there are it seems to me
things we can't stand on and ground
ourselves on even though that is not a
fixed ground they are certain
imperatives that we can or cannot accept
a covenant if you like we can enter into
of course all things can be broken but
there are consequences to those to that
breaking and so as we are here
attempting to understand what is a for
dn't of authenticity and what is afford
n't of or the presencing of authenticity
in relationship as amiable to a
reciprocal opening and this abductive
process of understanding we one thing I
think can
put forward is that a commitment to be
here now together at least for a certain
duration knowing that cutting the
duration itself is already limiting the
context if we take that to be truly what
we are doing so what does it mean to
then truly commit to being here with
each other and just how much are we able
to integrate through that process even
as someone drops into the space with the
context shifting and psyche unsettling
and chaos inducing fluxes apparitions of
the vulnerability of our existential
predicament both now and perhaps also
eternally so the commit
to really step in is not a flippant one
and this I suppose is not a bad place
for me to for me to stop this and see if
this is landed I it strikes me that what
what what you're talking about is a kind
of rigor and that it's a rigor that I I
have so much affection for because it's
it's a rigor for perceiving and looking
for maybe with that wonder that you were
speaking of earlier John hmm
you know interdependency is a lot of
differences a lot of vitality 'he's a
lot of interactions a lot of relational
messiness and it's not to be
underestimated the kind of the kind of
multi sensory perception that it takes
to pay attention in that way and so it's
you know it's not as if you can just do
complexity as an intellectual game right
it's if you don't allow that complexity
to be perceived through your own
complexity that is not just in words or
jargons or maps but also in stories and
music and unspoken sensed things and all
kinds of other information that's there
you need all of it
if you're gonna enter into that
integrity or that authenticity it's a
kind of alertness in the rigor and so I
guess that's what I'm kind of hearing
you say right off the bat what do you
think John what are you hearing well I'm
hearing something similar to that and
overlaps with it and I'm hearing the
commitment and I like the notion of
rigor I'm hearing that noir that you're
you talk about things I used the
language of kinds of knowing that are
not propositional there's procedural
knowing and respect travel and
participatory and I think what you're
saying is the knowing and I'm using
knowing that knowledge deliberately
knowing of complexity is something we
only know within and through our own
complexity right it's it's a
participatory knowing it's not just a
referential knowing and I think that's
really important and so I'm hearing that
the commitment therefore is a kind of
comprehensive commitment to I like this
notion of rigor about trying to bring I
well let me let me try it this way what
I heard when I heard that rigor and that
you took it to those deep levels in
response to Tim he's like I said I'm
hearing I'm hearing virtue I'm hearing
I'm hearing that we're virtue doesn't
mean the possession of a rule we reduced
virtue which were originally meant they
sort of person hole capacity and power
for dealing with you know the the messy
ill-defined situations of life and then
we reduced it to the possessions of sets
of rules and you know and you know sort
of content procedures and I think that's
why the Aristotelian model of the virtue
as kind of something that's always found
between different kinds of vices vices
of defect and vices of excess and so
it's it's
two is more like a virtual engine it
it's what constantly steers you between
the vicissitudes of a self-organizing
process so you don't fall out of it
that's and that's what I hear
Tim saying is is needed that people that
come into these the intention to commit
is necessary but nowhere sufficient for
being able to commit you need particular
skills and virtues in order to commit in
the way we're talking about here now I
don't want to and I want to build a you
know a catch-22 in here I think the
practice that Nora is talking about is a
way in which people can start to
cultivate but these virtues but I think
to meet the normative demand that Tim is
talking about I think we do need to talk
about virtue at some point that these
practices should result in people
carrying away in their person not
beliefs but carrying away skills and
virtues that transfer into multiple
contexts in your life and I you know I
think the meta virtue of course is
wisdom and so I that's what I think is
the normativity that I heard you
pointing towards Tim and I think when
you can when people can realize and I
mean that in both senses of the word
come to awareness and make real when
people can realize that these practices
our affording deeply affording of the
cultivation of of connectedness and the
virtues that would properly how's that
and and guide it I think that's deeply
motivating to people I think that's
deeply motivating to people I think that
goes back towards you know giving them a
taste but a taste of the good if you'll
allow me a platonic word and you know
what you know what Nora was talking
about sounded so similar to me - what
Iris Murdoch talks about when she talks
about the you know the the the necessity
for paying you know - for a particular
kind of complex attention and she it's
called the sovereignty of the good for a
reason she she allies that capacity with
the ability to orient towards the good
to love the good to be tempted by the
good
and I think when people get a taste for
this Tim that could really afford the
kind of commitment that you're talking
about that's what that's how that's what
I hear
yes yes um can I ask how I just think it
appropriate here to just check in and to
be conscious of everyone's time what are
we looking at over the next few minutes
here I'm I had us down to 5:30 so I I'm
coming up I'm coming up in sort of a
heart again I'm soon I don't want I mean
I don't want to be presumptive and I
don't want a corner Nora in any way or
you Tim but I'm happy to come back and
to have another discussion I found this
one
I'm incredibly rich and you could tell
at times it was it was really getting me
quite impassioned in the good sense of
the word
yes so nice to meet you so I love this
yeah long overdue what took us so long I
don't know the world intervenes in our
lives in ways that's happened so I I
mean I'm pretty much going to have to
leave soon Tim but Pete um I again I'm
not making a demand on anybody I'm just
speaking for myself I am committing if
it is desired to do one of these again I
enjoyed this thoroughly I think it's
fruitful and valuable and pertinent
given where we're at right now and so
you know and it doesn't have to be a
long time from now if if schedules
permit and people are willing and
wanting you know a few weeks from now
and I'm happy to do this again and pick
up on these threads and going yeah so
I'm just saying that right here right
now as a way of expressing my gratitude
by making a commitment yes I second that
sorry yeah grateful be honored well
thank you so much and as usual for me
with with so much with so much more to
say and in the acceptance at the time is
not now I will thank you so much for for
joining me this was for
an opportunity and intention to bring
together two people that I find to be to
possess no no shortage of beauty and
wisdom thank you
yes together it's always a pleasure to
see you Tim and it's been a great
pleasure meeting and getting into
dialogue with you Nora and I look
forward to doing it again
I do too John and thank you so much Tim
whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases